Tianyi Zhang

zty@seas.upenn.edu | https://tianyi0608.github.io/tianyizhang



HIGHLIGHTS

Expertise: Natural Language Processing 4 years in MSE and beyond Human Cognition 6 years in B.S., M.Ed.

• **Research Experience:** 4 projects in 4 years: Synopsis:

Event Extraction DARPA BETTER, USA, 20-22, publication [6]
Schema Induction DARPA KAIROS, USA, 22, leader, publication [5]
Natural to Symbolic Translation AI2, USA, 23, member & leader, publication [2,3]
Pretraining with NL-KG Reconstruction University of Bonn, Germany, 24 fall, publication [1]

• Research Interests: Understanding and Reasoning in Natural and Symbolic Language

Language Model Pretraining, Multimodality

Other human cognition and NLP related fields, including Robotics, CV

Happy to explore and confident to work well in varied tasks

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania | Philadelphia, America
 MSE in Data Science
 Sept. 2018 – Dec. 2022
 GPA: 3.97/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Chris Callison-Burch

M.Ed. in Learning Science and Technology GPA: 3.91/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Yasmin B. Kafai

• **Beijing Normal University** | Beijing, China Sept. 2014 – Jul. 2018

B.S. in Educational Technology GPA: 88/100

Advisor: Prof. Qian Fu

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Zhang, T., Mai, F., Flek, L., Pretraining Language Models with NL-KG-NL Reconstruction Loop. Paper in writing.
- [2] Zhang, T. *, Zhang, L. *, Hou, Z., Wang, Z., Gu, Y., Clark, P., Callison-Burch, C., and Tandon, N. (2024). PROC2PDDL: Open-Domain Planning Representations from Texts. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Natural Language Reasoning and Structured Explanations (NLRSE) (oral + poster).
- [3] Zhang, L., Jansen, P., **Zhang, T.**, Clark, P., Callison-Burch, C., Tandon, N. (2024). PDDLEGO: Iterative Planning in Textual Environments. In Proceedings of the 13th Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics (*SEM).
- [4] Jin, M., Kaul, M., Ramakrishnan, S., Jain, H., Chandrawat, S., Agarwal, I., **Zhang, T.**, Zhu, A., Callison-Burch, C. (2024). WorldWeaver: Procedural World Generation for Text Adventure Games using Large Language Models. In Proceedings of the 4th Wordplay: When Language Meets Games @ ACL 2024.
- [5] **Zhang, T.***, Tham, I. *, Hou, Z. *, Ren, J., Zhou, L., Xu, H., Zhang, L., Martin, L., Dror, R., Li, S., Ji, H., Palmer, M., Brown, S., Suchocki, R., and Callison-Burch, C. (2023). Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction. In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 3: System Demonstrations) (poster).
- [6] Zhang, T., Sulem, E., Roth, D. Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Lamarr Institute at University of Bonn

Pretraining Language Model through Unsupervised Text and Knowledge Graph Loop

- To enhance model's understanding and reasoning abilities on downstream tasks
- · Design pretraining pipeline imitating human learning: encoding-memorization-decoding
- Train encoder-decoder LMs on masked knowledge tuples and NL-KG-NL reconstruction objectives
- · Improve faithfulness and interpretability of black-box LMs
- Publication [1]: "Pretraining Language Models with NL-KG-NL Reconstruction Loop."

NLP Group at UPenn

May. 2022 – Jun. 2023

Natural to Symbolic Reasoning

- · To reason on events unfold: infer events with fine-grained entity-state
- Translate open-domain Natural Language text (wikiHow) to Symbolic Language (PDDL) with GPT-4
- Decompose the task into three stages: extraction, inference, and translation
- Identify strong text extraction and entity-state inference abilities with complex wikiHow text (~5000 words)
- · Acknowledge a weak translation capability to predefined symbolic predicates
- Improve the entity-state tracking using CoT and instructions on translation.
- · Publication [2][3]: "PROC2PDDL: Open-Domain Planning Representations from Texts."

Event Schema Induction

- To understand event relations: (semi-) automatically create event schema in high quality
- Design the scaffolds (cause, plan, procedure, effect, etc.) for GPT-3
- Apply SRL and constituency parsing to summarize and extract structured events
- · Build schema graphs by adding temporal relations to the events
- Iteratively prompt LM and merge graphs
- Design interface for human GPT interactive schema generation
- Improve accuracy and efficiency (1 hour to 15 mins per schema) and adopted by the UIUC group
- · Publication [5]: "Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction."

• Cognitive Computation Group at UPenn

Mar. 2020 - Dec. 2022

Event Extraction

- · To understand atomic events: extract events with 'who does what to whom'
- Identify and classify event triggers using sequence tagging
- · Design a pipeline: BIO identify event type classify model to replace the joint model
- · Improve performance with transfer learning on target language dataset, e.g., OntoNotesArabic
- Identify and classify event arguments using QA
- Design fixed questions for each argument role and convert the argument role labeling task to the Question-Answering task
- Build a pipeline model: has/no answer classification + has answer identification to replace has-and-no-answer joint model
- Improve performance with transfer learning on auxiliary QA datasets, e.g., SQuAD, QAMR

Event Data Augmentation

- To overcome the deficiency of event annotation data
- Design a pipeline approach: answer extraction (AE) and question generation (QG)
- Train AEwSRL-QG Bert-T5 model to extract QA pairs from unlabeled event text
- · Evaluate the augmented data on QA event extraction model
- Prove the effectiveness of the data augmentation approach (8k synthetic data exceeds 80k SQuAD data test on the ACE)
- · Publication [6]: "Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling."

Sept. 2024 -

WORK EXPERIENCE

•	Visiting Scholar	Lamarr Institute University of Bonn, Germany Advised by Prof. Lucie Flek	Sept. 2024 – Dec. 2024
		See the Research Experience section for details	
•	Research Assistant	NLP Group University of Pennsylvania, America See the Research Experience section for details	May. 2022 – Jun. 2023
		Cognitive Computation Group University of Pennsylvania	Mar. 2020 – Dec. 2022
		See the Research Experience section for details	
•	Teaching Assistant	CIS522 Deep Learning University of Pennsylvania, America	Jan. 2022 – May. 2022
	•	Design course materials and teach deep learning models in CV, NLP, RL, etc.	
	•	Hold Office Hours and group discussions each week.	
•	Data Analyst	SciStarter Philadelphia, America	Sep. 2018 – Apr. 2019
	•	Use the Python Pandas package to clean and analyze email log-in data (30,000 records).	
	·	Find the highest possibility of emails being checked is between 9 a.m. to 3 p.m., and within 1 day (over 80%). The most attractive topics are love, games, and high tech. The royalty of the subscriber is 50%.	